Alejandro David Tapia Talavera

adtapiatalavera@gmail.com (+51) 940323161

https://www.linkedin.com/in/alejandrotapiatalavera/

Summary

Software engineer with 5 years of experience in web development, data analysis, and cloud computing. Throughout my career, I have led both local and international projects across industries such as banking, healthcare, and automotive, focusing on developing and implementing compliance and risk management solutions. Proficient in technologies like ReactJS, AngularJS, .NET, and Azure, with a strong background in utilizing agile methodologies to deliver value. I pride myself on my commitment to quality, innovation, and collaborative teamwork, driving business growth and success.

Education

PUCP (Pontifical Catholic University of Peru) Bachelor of Software Engineering

Lima, Peru Aug 2021

Knowledge in Computer Science, Information Technology, System Information, and Software Engineering ACM areas. Proficient tackling a wide range of technical challenges.

Technical Skill

•	HTML
•	CSS

- AngularJS
- Python
- UX

C#

- Power BI
- SCRUM

- JavaScript
- .NET
- Tableau
- Azure Cloud

- Bootstrap ReactJS
- ORM (EF) **SOL** Server
- Alteryx
- Reveal

Professional Experience

Ernst & Young Senior – Software Engineer

Lima, Peru Jun 2021 – Present

- Lead the design and development of web platforms deployed in cloud environments with a primary focus on information protection, data integrity, performance, reliability, and confidentiality.
- Collaborate with experts in auditing, regulatory compliance, and data protection from various countries like Germany, the Netherlands, India, the United Kingdom, France, and the United States, to deliver tailored solutions to meet unique project requirements.
- Conduct thorough code reviews to maintain the organization of the source code and identify logic errors that could disrupt workflows.
- Actively participate in meetings with stakeholders, effectively communicating complex technical concepts in a clear and concise manner, making them easy to understand for a non-technical audience.
- Manage development projects using the Scrum framework, ensuring the quality and consistency of the solutions led.
- Assist in mentoring and providing technical guidance to junior developers, fostering their growth and contributing to a collaborative and productive team environment.
- Responsible for preparing time and cost estimates for development iterations, presenting them clearly and concisely to area managers to facilitate project continuation.
- Improved and optimized advanced algorithms to quickly detect irregularities, anomalies, and potential errors in complex journal entries, streamlining accurate and efficient auditing processes for a service deployed in Germany, increasing its usage by 10%.
- Conducted performance testing and optimization measures on telephone systems, enhancing the efficiency and reliability of communications.
- Lead the implementation and deployment of a Chatbot aimed at improving the services provided by the solutions department, with the goal of reducing man-hours by 20%.

Ernst & Young Lima, Peru

Staff – Software Engineer

Feb 2021 - Jun 2021

• Part of the development team that implemented platforms for three counties and one state in the United States, designed to review and approve funds for individuals and small businesses to mitigate the impact of the COVID-19 pandemic, supporting the country's relief programs.

- Collaborated with the audit team to create workflows aimed at analyzing their purchases and sales, detecting potential fraud schemes, and reducing analysis time by 83.3%.
- Implemented user-friendly dashboards, providing the audit team with clear and concise visualizations of audit findings, accelerating value delivery to clients.
- Led local teams in the design, development, and delivery of new functionalities for a platform used in the banking sector for risk management and action planning.

Ernst & Young
Lima, Peru
Intern – Software Engineer
Jan 2019 – Feb 2021

- Contributed to the design and development of a comprehensive risk assessment tool in collaboration with a US-based team, enabling the identification of gaps and the activation of action plans to effectively mitigate risks.
- Designed and developed interactive demos for multiple companies across various industries, contributing to a 50% growth in the area.
- Conducted client interviews to understand their specific needs and subsequently designed and implemented customized workflows to analyze their sales and purchase data.
- Developed and optimized workflows for sales and purchase data analysis, leveraging data cleansing and validation techniques to ensure the accuracy and integrity of the analyzed information.
- Participated in the review and update of documentation for implemented solutions, both local and international, serving as user guides for platform users and as knowledge resources for new team members.

Certificates

Deep Dive into Modern Web Development

In progress

The Deep Dive and Modern Web Development course has fourteen sections on web development and the current trends. All these sections have a certification and can be validated as credits in Helsinki University.

JavaScript Algorithms and Data Structures (Beta)

Aug 2024

The JavaScript Algorithms and Data Structures (Beta) validates three hundred hours of knowledge and practice using JavaScript to manage the DOM, to do functional or OOP programming, to manipulate strings, arrays and regular expressions.

Responsive Web Design

Dec 2023

The Responsive Web Design certificate validates three hundred hours of knowledge on how to manipulate HTML and CSS to create pretty, responsive and well-designed web pages.

Microsoft-Azure Fundamentals

Feb 2021

The Azure Administrator certificate validates expertise in managing and monitoring Microsoft Azure environments, including tasks such as implementing virtual networks and ensuring compliance.

CertiProf-Scrum Foundation Professional

Sep 2020

CertiProf's Scrum Foundation Professional certification validates knowledge of Scrum principles and Agile project management, providing a strong foundation for successful project delivery.

Cambridge-First Certificate in English

Nov 2013

FCE (First Certificate in English) from Cambridge Assessment English validates upper-intermediate English proficiency and is recognized globally by educational institutions and employers.

Additional Information

- Spanish Native
- English Advanced
- Portuguese Basic